<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Photographer.io Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-16T09:55:19+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.photographer.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert May]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@photographer.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[v1.1.0 has been released]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/16/v1-dot-1-0-has-been-released/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-16T09:29:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/16/v1-dot-1-0-has-been-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/afternoonrobot/photographer-io/releases/tag/v1.1.0">v1.1.0 has been released on our GitHub repo</a>. This is the first release since open sourcing <a href="https://www.photographer.io">Photographer.io</a> last week, and includes a large amount of bugfixes, a reasonable amount of internationalisation, and a small number of new features.</p>

<p>I have decided to aim for a tagged release around every 2 weeks, to give me a target to hit for adding new features and to provide stable points in the application&rsquo;s history for others to use. There is still a lot to do in relation to documentation, testing, and workflow improvements (such as actually tagging patch releases), but there has been a <em>lot</em> of improvements since the open source announcement.</p>

<p>If you want to get involved then all <a href="https://github.com/afternoonrobot/photographer-io">the code is available on GitHub under an MIT license</a>, or if you fancy translating the app to another language then <a href="https://www.transifex.com/projects/p/photographerio">come join us on Transifex</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dutch and Polish Language Support Now in Beta]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/13/dutch-and-polish-language-support-now-in-beta/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-13T23:25:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/13/dutch-and-polish-language-support-now-in-beta</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m really pleased to be able to announce that our first two options for languages have gone up on the site in beta. You can now browse <a href="https://www.photographer.io">Photographer.io</a> in <a href="https://www.photographer.io/nl_NL">Dutch</a> and <a href="https://www.photographer.io/pl">Polish</a>. This is the first step of integrating some of the fantastic work our <a href="https://www.transifex.com/projects/p/photographerio/">open source translators</a> have been doing and it&rsquo;s really exciting to be able to start offering the site in languages other than English. Photography is a universal medium and I want to provide a great experience for everybody around the world.</p>

<p>For these language releases I must thank <a href="https://www.transifex.com/accounts/profile/HiryuSingh/">HiryuSingh</a> for the Dutch translations, and <a href="https://www.transifex.com/accounts/profile/kocio/">kocio</a> for the Polish translations. I&rsquo;ll be finding a way to reward translators more in the future, as I&rsquo;m incredibly grateful for the work everyone has been putting into it.</p>

<p>As well as being able to select a language from the footer of every page, you can also set your default language via your account page:</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.photographer.io/images/posts/8/settings.png" alt="Account language option" /></p>

<p>If you see any rogue English words around the site then it&rsquo;s most likely due to me having missed out the key in the original English locale files. Please <a href="mailto:support@photographer.io">let me know</a> if you find any and I&rsquo;ll get them added in as soon as possible.</p>

<p>Want to help translate Photographer.io into your language, or suggest improvements to an existing one? The <a href="https://github.com/afternoonrobot/photographer-io">entire app is open source</a> and you can <a href="https://www.transifex.com/projects/p/photographerio/">join the translation team over on Transifex</a>. Any contribution is very much appreciated!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Translating Photographer.io]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/09/translating-photographer-dot-io/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-09T23:17:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/09/translating-photographer-dot-io</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to some hard-working and enthusiastic volunteers, <a href="https://www.transifex.com/projects/p/photographerio/">work has already begun on translating</a> the application into a variety of other languages. Anyone can join in and help translate the site into their favoured language!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m incredibly grateful to all the effort the translators are putting into this. I built the application from the start with an international audience in mind, and in theory enabling multi-lingual support is straight-forward once the translations are complete. The ability to switch the site language is planned for the next couple of weeks.</p>

<p>If you want to help out then <a href="https://www.transifex.com/projects/p/photographerio/">head on over to the Transifex page</a>. If your language doesn&rsquo;t have an active project yet then be the first to create it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We're now Open Source!]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/08/were-now-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-08T00:14:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/08/were-now-open-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As of yesterday <a href="https://www.photographer.io">Photographer.io</a> is now open source. I&rsquo;ve been meaning to release the source code for quite a while and it&rsquo;s a great relief to finally get it out there, even if it does reveal the currently woeful test suite. You can find the source <a href="https://github.com/afternoonrobot/photographer-io">on GitHub</a> under an MIT license.</p>

<p>There are a number of reasons why I wanted to open source this application:</p>

<h3>I&rsquo;d love to get other people involved in creating a great photography community.</h3>

<p>Opening up the source code to your contributions is really exciting to me. I&rsquo;ve always been open to suggestions and ideas (and the vast majority of the <a href="https://github.com/afternoonrobot/photographer-io/issues">open issue tickets on GitHub</a> are suggestions from members), and this will hopefully let others contribute in a meaningful way.</p>

<h3>It relieves some of the pressure on being the only developer on the project.</h3>

<p>If something were to happen to me, the project could still continue. I&rsquo;d hate to leave everyone in the lurch in the case of my unexpected demise.</p>

<h3>It will improve the quality and security of the site by opening the code to peer review.</h3>

<p>I care a lot about security and code quality, but talking about security and testing those claims are two very different subjects. If you find a security flaw then please get in touch at <a href="&#109;&#97;&#x69;&#108;&#116;&#111;&#58;&#x73;&#101;&#99;&#x75;&#114;&#105;&#x74;&#x79;&#x40;&#112;&#x68;&#x6f;&#x74;&#111;&#103;&#114;&#97;&#112;&#104;&#x65;&#x72;&#x2e;&#105;&#111;">&#x73;&#x65;&#99;&#x75;&#x72;&#105;&#x74;&#121;&#64;&#x70;&#104;&#x6f;&#116;&#x6f;&#103;&#x72;&#97;&#x70;&#104;&#x65;&#114;&#46;&#x69;&#111;</a>.</p>

<h3>It&rsquo;s great to finally have a project worth open sourcing.</h3>

<p>On a more selfish note; I&rsquo;m really excited to have something I feel is worth open sourcing. I&rsquo;ve spent 2 months working nearly every evening to get the site to a stable point and I&rsquo;m generally pleased with where it is (other than the dire test suite). There will always be a part of me that feels a little apprehensive about offering up the code I&rsquo;ve spent so much time on recently, but I&rsquo;m confident that this is the right thing to do.</p>

<h2>Getting involved</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s lots to do, including documentation and testing, but it&rsquo;s hopefully in a state where you can at least look through the code and get an understanding of what&rsquo;s going on. If you have any questions then please <a href="http://twitter.com/photographer_io">ask away</a>. I&rsquo;ll make sure to put up some notes on how to contribute shortly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Terms of Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/07/terms-of-service/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-07T18:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/07/terms-of-service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Our <a href="https://www.photographer.io/terms">Terms of Service</a> are now live. They are likely to change and be revised over time, and I&rsquo;m open to feedback or questions regarding them. There shouldn&rsquo;t be anything surprising in there; the main mantra being: <em>Photographer.io won&rsquo;t steal your photos. Don&rsquo;t steal other people&rsquo;s photos.</em></p>

<p>Any questions? <a href="mailto:support@photographer.io">Shoot us an email!</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Changing Server Stacks is Not Fun]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/19/changing-server-stacks-is-not-fun/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-19T23:46:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/19/changing-server-stacks-is-not-fun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every evening for the past week has been spent preparing to move <a href="https://www.photographer.io">Photographer.io</a> to a new server architecture. We were previously on <a href="https://www.heroku.com">Heroku</a>, and we&rsquo;re now running on a custom server setup on <a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/?refcode=0d41e836e212">Digital Ocean</a>.</p>

<p>The past few days have made me both excited and incredibly frustrated with running a web application. Here&rsquo;s a few details on why.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Heroku</h3>

<p>I like Heroku. We use Heroku a lot <a href="http://wearebarenaked.com">at my day job</a> and it&rsquo;s a really good way of launching an app. It is, however,  <em>incredibly expensive</em>. Now I&rsquo;m talking primarily about web/worker processes here, as I think <a href="https://postgres.heroku.com">Heroku Postgres</a> is actually reasonable value and it&rsquo;s a fantastic service. I understand that there&rsquo;s a lot more to the stack on Heroku than just running your web process, but it&rsquo;s $35 a month for poorer performance than what you can achieve for $5 on Digital Ocean, or $15 on most other VPS providers.</p>

<h3>Digital Ocean</h3>

<p>It&rsquo;s very cheap. This is a real boon for me as it lets me run the server stack I want; load balancers, web servers, redundant database servers, and a general utility/cache server; all for less than half what it costs on Heroku. And the performance benefits that come along with it are just the icing on the cake.</p>

<p>Digital Ocean are currently experiencing massive growth and I&rsquo;m sure that&rsquo;s going to result in a bit of instability over the next few weeks/months whilst they scale. I&rsquo;m not too fussed right now though, as Photographer.io still hasn&rsquo;t formally launched or been promoted in any significant way. It&rsquo;s a good time to try out a new architecture and get used to its quirks before (hopefully) gaining a lot of traffic.</p>

<h3>The Pain</h3>

<p>I must admit that I&rsquo;m not the happiest of sysadmins. There are some pieces of software which are a joy to set up (<a href="http://haproxy.1wt.eu/">HAProxy</a>, <a href="http://memcached.org/">Memcached</a>, <a href="http://redis.io">Redis</a>), and then there are those which make me swear and perform any number of hexes on the developers who designed them (<a href="http://www.postgresql.org/">PostgreSQL</a>). Having to set up my own Postgres server made me seriously regret ever having chosen it; MariaDB would have been a much simpler choice.</p>

<p>I have not suffered in vain, however, as the site is now significantly quicker to respond than it was whilst on Heroku and I&rsquo;m much happier with the costs involved.</p>

<h3>The New Setup</h3>

<p>This is what&rsquo;s currently running for the initial launch of this stack:</p>

<ul>
<li>2x 512MB HAProxy Load Balancers (nothing clever for failover at the moment, just a DNS toggle)</li>
<li>2x 2GB Web/Worker Servers, running Ruby 2.0, Puma, Sidekiq</li>
<li>2x 1GB Database Servers, Postgres 9.2</li>
<li>1x 512MB Utility Server, Memcached/Redis</li>
</ul>


<p>It&rsquo;s not perfect but it leaves plenty of room for scaling. I&rsquo;d like to move over to JRuby to make better use of the resources available but there are a few bugs I need to iron out before I can switch.</p>

<h4>Other Bits</h4>

<p><a href="https://www.cloudflare.com">CloudFlare</a> sits in front of the load balancers to help provide a variety of extra services (notably better security). Backups of data are handled using <a href="https://www.tarsnap.com">Tarsnap</a> for excellent data security and as I&rsquo;ve got nothing but great things to say about it.</p>

<h3>Token Poorly Labelled Charts</h3>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a totally unreliable but somewhat interesting comparison of the past hour, from two days ago whilst running on Heroku:</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.photographer.io/images/posts/7/heroku_stack.png" alt="Heroku Performance" /></p>

<p>And the same data for the past hour today on Digital Ocean (when I remembered to re-enable NewRelic):</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.photographer.io/images/posts/7/do_stack.png" alt="Digital Ocean Performance" /></p>

<p>Finally the performance data is starting to look how you&rsquo;d expect from an application written in a modern scripting language: the application is by far the slowest component.</p>

<h3>Processing Photos Was Expensive</h3>

<p>On Heroku processing the often very large photos people uploaded was quite expensive. If someone batch uploads 100 photographs, a worker will be churning away for quite a while on a number of jobs at once. To manage this at all on Heroku required a 1GB worker dyno at $72 per month. On Digital Ocean I&rsquo;m running the workers on the same servers as the web processes (2GB RAM shared between the processes) and it&rsquo;s $20 per month. You could run a server with 8GB of RAM for $8 more than 1GB costs you on Heroku.</p>

<h3>Time Will Tell</h3>

<p>Now that the switch is complete, I&rsquo;ll be spending the next few weeks keeping a close eye on log files and server stats (<a href="https://boundary.com">Boundary</a> is pretty cool, though I just look at the pretty graphs) and adjusting things as I go along. One of the best things I&rsquo;ve taken away from this is that Digital Ocean is letting me play at running a server architecture more akin to those run by high traffic apps without having to stump up the cash to do so. It&rsquo;s certainly more complicated than running on Heroku, and I&rsquo;m really hoping that technologies like <a href="http://docker.io">Docker</a> gain a lot of traction in the near future. Setting up this server stack over the past week brought me very close to chucking it all in and going to live in the woods and carve wooden spoons*.</p>

<p><sup><a href="https://www.photographer.io/photographs/2782">I do that anyway</a>, but it&rsquo;s not a hugely profitable career</sup></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Username Support]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/08/username-support/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-08T18:14:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/08/username-support</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Usernames are now live! Finally, you can access your public profile via <a href="https://www.photographer.io/u/robotmay">https://www.photographer.io/u/robotmay</a> rather than /users/1.</p>

<p>To facilitate this change I&rsquo;ve added a new &lsquo;username&rsquo; field, which must be a unique, lowercase name containing only letters, numbers, and underscores. This will then be used in URLs across the site. Your first username has been automatically generated from your current display name, but you can change this (up to 2 times) from your account settings page.</p>

<p>Accessing a page via an old username will redirect to your new one. In the future old names will be freed up for new users to take them after a certain length of time.</p>

<p>If you have any questions about how this system works; get in touch!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google+]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/05/google-plus/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-05T08:56:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/05/google-plus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://plus.google.com/100673063979311454242"><img src="http://blog.photographer.io/images/posts/6/plus_profile.png" alt="Google+ profile" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://plus.google.com/100673063979311454242">Photographer.io is now on Google+</a>. This is the first bit of social integration that I&rsquo;ve added to the site so far, and I started with Google+ for two good reasons:</p>

<ol>
<li>There are a lot of photographers on Google+</li>
<li>Google is shifting a lot of their search engine focus to integration with Google+</li>
</ol>


<!-- more -->


<p>There are two bits of integration so far, though only the first is currently live on the site:</p>

<h3>Currently Live</h3>

<h4>Share Button</h4>

<p><img src="http://blog.photographer.io/images/posts/6/share_button.png" alt="Google+ share button" /></p>

<p>First you&rsquo;ll notice that there&rsquo;s now a share button underneath every photograph. This is where other options will also go in the future. The photo pages now have extra markup to help Google find the relevant content in a page, so it picks up on the image accurately.</p>

<h4>Sharing Options</h4>

<p><img src="http://blog.photographer.io/images/posts/6/social_options.png" alt="User options" /></p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t want to see social buttons anywhere on the site? You can disable it in your account settings. I understand some folks aren&rsquo;t a fan of these social sites (I block them myself in many places) and I take privacy concerns very seriously.</p>

<h3>Coming Soon</h3>

<h4>Activity Integration</h4>

<p>Google+ allows your application to automatically post user activity (i.e. creating new photos) to G+. This requires you to sign in to your G+ account via Photographer.io. It&rsquo;s fully integrated and working, it just doesn&rsquo;t seem to have much of a point; those activities don&rsquo;t appear anywhere except an obscure page buried deep in their UI. I&rsquo;ll enable this in the near future once I&rsquo;ve tested it some more, on the off chance that someone finds it useful.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DNS Fixes and Improvements]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/04/dns-fixes-and-improvements/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-04T09:05:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/04/dns-fixes-and-improvements</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After an interesting day of DNS issues with our DNS host yesterday, I&rsquo;ve finally resolved the issues. I&rsquo;ve migrated our DNS over to a new provider and I believe everything should be resolving correctly now, including the root domain.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I&rsquo;ve moved the DNS over to <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com">CloudFlare</a> as they have proved stable for me in the past, though I may consider other alternatives in a week or so once the pain of migrating the DNS records twice in one day subsides (it wasn&rsquo;t fun).</p>

<p>However there are some positives to take from yesterday:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>It persuaded me to switch back to using a non-root domain as the primary way of accessing the site. Using the www subdomain may not be as neat looking, but it scales more effectively with cloud hosting services and doesn&rsquo;t require any weird tweaks. Using the root domain was one of the reasons we suffered so much downtime yesterday, as <a href="http://dnsimple.com">DNSimple</a> uses a custom ALIAS record for handling root domains pointing to CNAME records, and this service died first when they were attacked.</p></li>
<li><p>New CDN configuration which doesn&rsquo;t fall back on the root domain, due to the problems mentioned above.</p></li>
<li><p>It happened whilst Photographer.io is still in beta. I&rsquo;m glad I&rsquo;ve been able to find out what needs fixing if the DNS provider goes down, and I&rsquo;ll be working on a better failover for the future.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>My apologies for the extended downtime yesterday. Let me know if you have any questions about the downtime or the solutions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DNS Resolution Problems]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/03/dns-resolution-problems/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-03T14:41:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/03/dns-resolution-problems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past hour our DNS host (<a href="http://dnsimple.com">DNSimple.com</a>) has been suffering a large Distributed Denial of Service attack on its nameservers. They&rsquo;ve managed to get basic service back up, but a component that is used to point the root domain (photographer.io) is currently disabled. I&rsquo;ve modified the DNS settings for now so that <a href="https://www.photographer.io">www.photographer.io</a> still resolves correctly, though the root domain will remain down until they&rsquo;ve fixed this issue.</p>

<p>My apologies for the downtime; I&rsquo;ll be looking for a way to prevent this causing such a detrimental effect in future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notifications for Favourites]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/02/notifications-for-favourites/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-02T10:50:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/02/notifications-for-favourites</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Other users will now be notified when you have favourited one of their photographs. I realise some people may not want their favourites to be public, and so if you don&rsquo;t want to notify them you can disable this via an option in your account settings.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.photographer.io/images/posts/5/notification.png" alt="Favourites notification" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Find Photographs Looking For Feedback]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/01/find-photographs-looking-for-feedback/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-01T10:37:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/01/find-photographs-looking-for-feedback</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A quick but helpful improvement to start off the weekend!</p>

<p>I noticed quite a lot of comment threads being opened up on photos, but they were quite difficult to find. I&rsquo;ve added a new option to the Explore menu which will help you <a href="https://photographer.io/photographs/seeking_feedback">find photographs which are open to your feedback</a>:</p>

<p><a href="https://photographer.io/photographs/seeking_feedback"><img src="http://blog.photographer.io/images/posts/4/current_explore_menu.png" alt="Current explore menu" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Notifications]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/05/31/introducing-notifications/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-31T00:03:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/05/31/introducing-notifications</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This evening I&rsquo;ve knuckled down and built a notifications system similar to what you may have used on sites like Facebook. I&rsquo;ll be making lots of use of it throughout the site, though at the moment it&rsquo;s used primarily for letting you know when someone has commented on your photos.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.photographer.io/images/posts/3/notification_panel.png" alt="Notification pane" /></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>For more important notifications you will be sent an email about it, however you can disable this if you like:</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.photographer.io/images/posts/3/notification_option.png" alt="Notification options" /></p>

<p>Let me know if you find any bugs with it, or have any suggestions for how it can be used across the site.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Commenting on Photographer.io: A Slightly Different Approach]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/05/29/commenting-on-photographer-dot-io-a-slightly-different-approach/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-29T19:42:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/05/29/commenting-on-photographer-dot-io-a-slightly-different-approach</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I initially announced the beta of <a href="https://photographer.io">Photographer.io</a> on <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/photography/comments/1dvms3/ive_built_a_new_photo_sharing_community_in_the/">Reddit</a> a few weeks back, one of the most popular discussions was on how the commenting system should work once it&rsquo;s implemented. It was nice to know I&rsquo;m not the only one who doesn&rsquo;t enjoy the current state of commenting on other sites, and I spent a good couple of weeks planning out possible solutions.</p>

<p>On Friday I launched the first iteration of a commenting system, and it&rsquo;s hopefully a slightly different approach. Let me know what you think!</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Disabled by default</h2>

<p>First, commenting is entirely opt-in at this time whilst it&rsquo;s in testing. I&rsquo;ve been taking this approach with nearly every new feature implemented so far; new features are often disabled by default for existing users to prevent any complaints surrounding privacy, or negatively affecting those users&#8217; experience on the site.</p>

<p>However there is another reason why it&rsquo;s disabled by default; the subject system.</p>

<h2>Commenting with a purpose</h2>

<p><img src="http://blog.photographer.io/images/posts/1/commenting_options.png" alt="Commenting options in the control panel" /></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not exactly beautiful right now, but this is what you&rsquo;ll see when you go to edit a photograph in your control panel. If you wish to enable commenting, you must set between one and three subjects for commenters to respond to. Consider this more like a traditional thread on a message board; a specific subject for other users to comment on.</p>

<p>What subjects you use is up to you; maybe you just want general comments like you get elsewhere, or perhaps you want constructive criticism of your technique, your colouring, or help identifying that pesky subject:</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.photographer.io/images/posts/1/comments_form.png" alt="Comments form on the front end" /></p>

<p>Want to try it out? <a href="https://photographer.io/account/sign_up">Create an account</a> and feel free to <a href="https://photographer.io/photographs/2423">test it on the photograph shown above</a>.</p>

<p>Pretty much every website in existence has the ability to &lsquo;Like&rsquo; or &lsquo;Favourite&rsquo; or, in the case of Photographer.io, &lsquo;Recommend&rsquo; content. So why should the commenting system be open to an endless stream of comments like &lsquo;OMG LOVE IT&rsquo;, &lsquo;Great&rsquo;, or &lsquo;It&rsquo;s like dolphins and rainbows hugging in my soul&#8221;? I&rsquo;ll be the first to admit that sometimes I really just want to tell somebody in my own words why I love their photo so much, and there will be a private messaging system to allow you to do that soon. However, a comment is a public entity; on many other sites whatever you post is visible right underneath someone else&rsquo;s work. Shouldn&rsquo;t they have a say in what appears there?</p>

<h2>Moderated by you</h2>

<p><img src="http://blog.photographer.io/images/posts/1/unpublished_comment.png" alt="Unpublished comment" /></p>

<p>You&rsquo;re in control of which comments are publicly visible. All submitted comments are, by default, visible only to the submitter, the owner of the photograph, and, if it&rsquo;s a reply, the person to whom you are replying. The owner of the photograph then decides whether to make the comment visible to everyone, or whether to keep it private. Perhaps this will result in valid criticism being kept private, but is that such a bad thing? I don&rsquo;t want new photographers to be put off of experimenting or learning by forcing them to have all critique visible on their photos; that should be up to them to decide.</p>

<h2>Improvements coming soon</h2>

<h4>Notifications</h4>

<p>Right now you&rsquo;ll be notified by email of every new comment made on your photographs. There will be an opt-out for this in future, and a built-in notifications panel similar to what you have on Facebook or GitHub.</p>

<h4>Reporting</h4>

<p>A reporting system is planned for the near future to allow you to report abuse of the commenting (and photograph) system.</p>

<h4>More configuration options</h4>

<p>In future I&rsquo;d like to give users the ability to set default subjects for their photos so that they can enable comments by default. The number of subjects allowed may also become more flexible.</p>

<h4>Email responses</h4>

<p>I&rsquo;ll also be looking to allow users to respond to comments via email to make it easier to hold a conversation with commenters on your photographs.</p>

<h2>Feedback</h2>

<p>What do you think? This is clearly still a work in progress but I&rsquo;d love to get some opinions about how it works and what you would do to improve it.</p>

<p>I am entirely open to feedback, ideas, and bug reports. You can reach me on Twitter as <a href="http://twitter.com/robotmay">@robotmay</a> or via email at <a href="mailto:rob@photographer.io"><a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#108;&#x74;&#x6f;&#58;&#x72;&#111;&#98;&#x40;&#112;&#x68;&#x6f;&#x74;&#x6f;&#103;&#114;&#97;&#x70;&#104;&#101;&#x72;&#x2e;&#105;&#111;">&#114;&#111;&#x62;&#x40;&#x70;&#x68;&#x6f;&#x74;&#x6f;&#x67;&#114;&#97;&#112;&#104;&#101;&#x72;&#46;&#x69;&#x6f;</a></a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA['Likes' are a Flawed Currency]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/05/26/likes-are-a-flawed-currency/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-26T17:01:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/05/26/likes-are-a-flawed-currency</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The &lsquo;Like&rsquo; as a concept is largely worthless. A &lsquo;Like&rsquo; has no value, no cost for doling out. &lsquo;Liking&rsquo; your content costs me nothing, so what&rsquo;s to stop me from &lsquo;Liking&rsquo; everything I see without considering how it affects the popularity of that content?</p>

<p>Like it or not (pun not initially intended), the ways in which many sites rank and suggest content is now often based heavily on &lsquo;Likes&rsquo;.</p>

<h2>Introducing &lsquo;Recommendations&rsquo;</h2>

<p><img src="http://blog.photographer.io/images/posts/2/recommend_button.png" alt="Recommendation button" /></p>

<p>Recommendations on <a href="https://photographer.io">Photographer.io</a> are akin to &lsquo;Likes&rsquo; elsewhere, though with a subtle difference: they are finite.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>10 per day</h3>

<p>Right now every user is limited to a maximum of 10 recommendations per day. This default will probably change in time once I have a better understanding of how many are used on average.</p>

<h3>Value in scarcity</h3>

<p>Because you can only click &lsquo;Recommend&rsquo; 10 times in a day, you can&rsquo;t go gallavanting about throwing them hither and thither; they are to be reserved for the photos which you think other users should see.</p>

<h3>Ranking impact</h3>

<p>Recommendations affect the ranking of photographs and places them into the <a href="https://photographer.io/photographs/recommended">Recommended</a> section of Photographer.io. I&rsquo;m very keen to ensure new users, lesser-known users, and more obscure photographs are just as easily discovered as the most popular photos/members. A recommendation carries more weight than views or favouriting and will help other people discover the great content you found.</p>

<p>A subject I&rsquo;ll also expand on in future is how the score of photographs (used in the rankings) diminishes over time to improve the visibility of newer content.</p>

<h3>Fairness</h3>

<p>You don&rsquo;t have to be an incredibly active user in order to have an impact, and that&rsquo;s how it should be. Popular photographs won&rsquo;t be as largely dictated by how many followers or friends you have.</p>

<h3>Recommendations vs. Favourites</h3>

<p>Photographer.io also features a &lsquo;Favourites&rsquo; system. Favourites are your personal way of saving the photos you love to a place where you can easily find them again. A recommendation differs in that it doesn&rsquo;t necessarily have to be a photograph that you love, but more so a photograph which you believe is technically good and should be seen by other people.</p>

<h2>Why does this matter?</h2>

<p>It might just be me, but it feels as if &lsquo;Likes&rsquo; have devalued a lot of content across the internet. In many places, it&rsquo;s not altogther that much different from a store points card; a way of tracking what you like and using it to target adverts towards you.</p>

<p>I want users to have a meaningful impact on the site and for their recommendations to matter. This feature is far from complete, but I think it&rsquo;s a step in the right direction.</p>

<h2>Feedback</h2>

<p>What do you think? I&rsquo;m always open to feedback, ideas, or bug reports.</p>

<p>You can reach me on Twitter as <a href="http://twitter.com/robotmay">@robotmay</a> or via email at <a href="mailto:rob@photographer.io"><a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x72;&#111;&#98;&#x40;&#x70;&#x68;&#x6f;&#116;&#111;&#x67;&#x72;&#x61;&#x70;&#104;&#x65;&#114;&#46;&#105;&#111;">&#114;&#111;&#x62;&#64;&#x70;&#104;&#x6f;&#116;&#111;&#103;&#114;&#x61;&#112;&#x68;&#x65;&#x72;&#46;&#105;&#x6f;</a></a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
