<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: New Features | Photographer.io Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/blog/categories/new-features/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-14T09:16:13+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.photographer.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert May]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@photographer.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dutch and Polish Language Support Now in Beta]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/13/dutch-and-polish-language-support-now-in-beta/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-13T23:25:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/13/dutch-and-polish-language-support-now-in-beta</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m really pleased to be able to announce that our first two options for languages have gone up on the site in beta. You can now browse <a href="https://www.photographer.io">Photographer.io</a> in <a href="https://www.photographer.io/nl_NL">Dutch</a> and <a href="https://www.photographer.io/pl">Polish</a>. This is the first step of integrating some of the fantastic work our <a href="https://www.transifex.com/projects/p/photographerio/">open source translators</a> have been doing and it&rsquo;s really exciting to be able to start offering the site in languages other than English. Photography is a universal medium and I want to provide a great experience for everybody around the world.</p>

<p>For these language releases I must thank <a href="https://www.transifex.com/accounts/profile/HiryuSingh/">HiryuSingh</a> for the Dutch translations, and <a href="https://www.transifex.com/accounts/profile/kocio/">kocio</a> for the Polish translations. I&rsquo;ll be finding a way to reward translators more in the future, as I&rsquo;m incredibly grateful for the work everyone has been putting into it.</p>

<p>As well as being able to select a language from the footer of every page, you can also set your default language via your account page:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/8/settings.png" alt="Account language option" /></p>

<p>If you see any rogue English words around the site then it&rsquo;s most likely due to me having missed out the key in the original English locale files. Please <a href="mailto:support@photographer.io">let me know</a> if you find any and I&rsquo;ll get them added in as soon as possible.</p>

<p>Want to help translate Photographer.io into your language, or suggest improvements to an existing one? The <a href="https://github.com/afternoonrobot/photographer-io">entire app is open source</a> and you can <a href="https://www.transifex.com/projects/p/photographerio/">join the translation team over on Transifex</a>. Any contribution is very much appreciated!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Username Support]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/08/username-support/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-08T18:14:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/08/username-support</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Usernames are now live! Finally, you can access your public profile via <a href="https://www.photographer.io/u/robotmay">https://www.photographer.io/u/robotmay</a> rather than /users/1.</p>

<p>To facilitate this change I&rsquo;ve added a new &lsquo;username&rsquo; field, which must be a unique, lowercase name containing only letters, numbers, and underscores. This will then be used in URLs across the site. Your first username has been automatically generated from your current display name, but you can change this (up to 2 times) from your account settings page.</p>

<p>Accessing a page via an old username will redirect to your new one. In the future old names will be freed up for new users to take them after a certain length of time.</p>

<p>If you have any questions about how this system works; get in touch!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notifications for Favourites]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/02/notifications-for-favourites/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-02T10:50:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/02/notifications-for-favourites</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Other users will now be notified when you have favourited one of their photographs. I realise some people may not want their favourites to be public, and so if you don&rsquo;t want to notify them you can disable this via an option in your account settings.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/5/notification.png" alt="Favourites notification" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Find Photographs Looking For Feedback]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/01/find-photographs-looking-for-feedback/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-01T10:37:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/06/01/find-photographs-looking-for-feedback</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A quick but helpful improvement to start off the weekend!</p>

<p>I noticed quite a lot of comment threads being opened up on photos, but they were quite difficult to find. I&rsquo;ve added a new option to the Explore menu which will help you <a href="https://photographer.io/photographs/seeking_feedback">find photographs which are open to your feedback</a>:</p>

<p><a href="https://photographer.io/photographs/seeking_feedback"><img src="/images/posts/4/current_explore_menu.png" alt="Current explore menu" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Notifications]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/05/31/introducing-notifications/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-31T00:03:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/05/31/introducing-notifications</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This evening I&rsquo;ve knuckled down and built a notifications system similar to what you may have used on sites like Facebook. I&rsquo;ll be making lots of use of it throughout the site, though at the moment it&rsquo;s used primarily for letting you know when someone has commented on your photos.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/3/notification_panel.png" alt="Notification pane" /></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>For more important notifications you will be sent an email about it, however you can disable this if you like:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/3/notification_option.png" alt="Notification options" /></p>

<p>Let me know if you find any bugs with it, or have any suggestions for how it can be used across the site.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
