<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: News | Photographer.io Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/blog/categories/news/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-16T09:55:19+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.photographer.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert May]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@photographer.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Translating Photographer.io]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/09/translating-photographer-dot-io/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-09T23:17:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/09/translating-photographer-dot-io</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to some hard-working and enthusiastic volunteers, <a href="https://www.transifex.com/projects/p/photographerio/">work has already begun on translating</a> the application into a variety of other languages. Anyone can join in and help translate the site into their favoured language!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m incredibly grateful to all the effort the translators are putting into this. I built the application from the start with an international audience in mind, and in theory enabling multi-lingual support is straight-forward once the translations are complete. The ability to switch the site language is planned for the next couple of weeks.</p>

<p>If you want to help out then <a href="https://www.transifex.com/projects/p/photographerio/">head on over to the Transifex page</a>. If your language doesn&rsquo;t have an active project yet then be the first to create it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We're now Open Source!]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/08/were-now-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-08T00:14:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/08/were-now-open-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As of yesterday <a href="https://www.photographer.io">Photographer.io</a> is now open source. I&rsquo;ve been meaning to release the source code for quite a while and it&rsquo;s a great relief to finally get it out there, even if it does reveal the currently woeful test suite. You can find the source <a href="https://github.com/afternoonrobot/photographer-io">on GitHub</a> under an MIT license.</p>

<p>There are a number of reasons why I wanted to open source this application:</p>

<h3>I&rsquo;d love to get other people involved in creating a great photography community.</h3>

<p>Opening up the source code to your contributions is really exciting to me. I&rsquo;ve always been open to suggestions and ideas (and the vast majority of the <a href="https://github.com/afternoonrobot/photographer-io/issues">open issue tickets on GitHub</a> are suggestions from members), and this will hopefully let others contribute in a meaningful way.</p>

<h3>It relieves some of the pressure on being the only developer on the project.</h3>

<p>If something were to happen to me, the project could still continue. I&rsquo;d hate to leave everyone in the lurch in the case of my unexpected demise.</p>

<h3>It will improve the quality and security of the site by opening the code to peer review.</h3>

<p>I care a lot about security and code quality, but talking about security and testing those claims are two very different subjects. If you find a security flaw then please get in touch at <a href="&#109;&#97;&#x69;&#x6c;&#x74;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#115;&#101;&#99;&#117;&#114;&#x69;&#116;&#121;&#64;&#x70;&#104;&#111;&#x74;&#111;&#x67;&#x72;&#x61;&#x70;&#x68;&#x65;&#114;&#x2e;&#x69;&#x6f;">&#x73;&#101;&#99;&#117;&#x72;&#105;&#x74;&#x79;&#64;&#x70;&#x68;&#x6f;&#116;&#x6f;&#x67;&#114;&#x61;&#112;&#104;&#101;&#114;&#x2e;&#x69;&#x6f;</a>.</p>

<h3>It&rsquo;s great to finally have a project worth open sourcing.</h3>

<p>On a more selfish note; I&rsquo;m really excited to have something I feel is worth open sourcing. I&rsquo;ve spent 2 months working nearly every evening to get the site to a stable point and I&rsquo;m generally pleased with where it is (other than the dire test suite). There will always be a part of me that feels a little apprehensive about offering up the code I&rsquo;ve spent so much time on recently, but I&rsquo;m confident that this is the right thing to do.</p>

<h2>Getting involved</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s lots to do, including documentation and testing, but it&rsquo;s hopefully in a state where you can at least look through the code and get an understanding of what&rsquo;s going on. If you have any questions then please <a href="http://twitter.com/photographer_io">ask away</a>. I&rsquo;ll make sure to put up some notes on how to contribute shortly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Terms of Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/07/terms-of-service/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-07T18:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/07/07/terms-of-service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Our <a href="https://www.photographer.io/terms">Terms of Service</a> are now live. They are likely to change and be revised over time, and I&rsquo;m open to feedback or questions regarding them. There shouldn&rsquo;t be anything surprising in there; the main mantra being: <em>Photographer.io won&rsquo;t steal your photos. Don&rsquo;t steal other people&rsquo;s photos.</em></p>

<p>Any questions? <a href="mailto:support@photographer.io">Shoot us an email!</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
