<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Features | Photographer.io Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/blog/categories/features/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-01T10:44:30+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.photographer.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert May]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@photographer.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA['Likes' are a Flawed Currency]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/05/26/likes-are-a-flawed-currency/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-26T17:01:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.photographer.io/posts/2013/05/26/likes-are-a-flawed-currency</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The &lsquo;Like&rsquo; as a concept is largely worthless. A &lsquo;Like&rsquo; has no value, no cost for doling out. &lsquo;Liking&rsquo; your content costs me nothing, so what&rsquo;s to stop me from &lsquo;Liking&rsquo; everything I see without considering how it affects the popularity of that content?</p>

<p>Like it or not (pun not initially intended), the ways in which many sites rank and suggest content is now often based heavily on &lsquo;Likes&rsquo;.</p>

<h2>Introducing &lsquo;Recommendations&rsquo;</h2>

<p><img src="/images/posts/2/recommend_button.png" alt="Recommendation button" /></p>

<p>Recommendations on <a href="https://photographer.io">Photographer.io</a> are akin to &lsquo;Likes&rsquo; elsewhere, though with a subtle difference: they are finite.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>10 per day</h3>

<p>Right now every user is limited to a maximum of 10 recommendations per day. This default will probably change in time once I have a better understanding of how many are used on average.</p>

<h3>Value in scarcity</h3>

<p>Because you can only click &lsquo;Recommend&rsquo; 10 times in a day, you can&rsquo;t go gallavanting about throwing them hither and thither; they are to be reserved for the photos which you think other users should see.</p>

<h3>Ranking impact</h3>

<p>Recommendations affect the ranking of photographs and places them into the <a href="https://photographer.io/photographs/recommended">Recommended</a> section of Photographer.io. I&rsquo;m very keen to ensure new users, lesser-known users, and more obscure photographs are just as easily discovered as the most popular photos/members. A recommendation carries more weight than views or favouriting and will help other people discover the great content you found.</p>

<p>A subject I&rsquo;ll also expand on in future is how the score of photographs (used in the rankings) diminishes over time to improve the visibility of newer content.</p>

<h3>Fairness</h3>

<p>You don&rsquo;t have to be an incredibly active user in order to have an impact, and that&rsquo;s how it should be. Popular photographs won&rsquo;t be as largely dictated by how many followers or friends you have.</p>

<h3>Recommendations vs. Favourites</h3>

<p>Photographer.io also features a &lsquo;Favourites&rsquo; system. Favourites are your personal way of saving the photos you love to a place where you can easily find them again. A recommendation differs in that it doesn&rsquo;t necessarily have to be a photograph that you love, but more so a photograph which you believe is technically good and should be seen by other people.</p>

<h2>Why does this matter?</h2>

<p>It might just be me, but it feels as if &lsquo;Likes&rsquo; have devalued a lot of content across the internet. In many places, it&rsquo;s not altogther that much different from a store points card; a way of tracking what you like and using it to target adverts towards you.</p>

<p>I want users to have a meaningful impact on the site and for their recommendations to matter. This feature is far from complete, but I think it&rsquo;s a step in the right direction.</p>

<h2>Feedback</h2>

<p>What do you think? I&rsquo;m always open to feedback, ideas, or bug reports.</p>

<p>You can reach me on Twitter as <a href="http://twitter.com/robotmay">@robotmay</a> or via email at <a href="mailto:rob@photographer.io"><a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#x69;&#108;&#116;&#111;&#58;&#114;&#111;&#x62;&#64;&#x70;&#104;&#111;&#x74;&#x6f;&#x67;&#x72;&#x61;&#x70;&#104;&#101;&#x72;&#x2e;&#x69;&#x6f;">&#x72;&#x6f;&#98;&#64;&#112;&#104;&#x6f;&#x74;&#111;&#x67;&#114;&#97;&#112;&#104;&#101;&#114;&#x2e;&#105;&#x6f;</a></a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
